

<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd" >


<p>This Guidance page aims to clarify the definition of the Belgian laboratory result.
It concerns the construction of a laboratory report in the HL7 FHIR format.</p>
<p>Examples are sometimes given in JSON or XML format but it SHALL be understood all structures can be expressed in both as per the FHIR standard.</p>
<p>
The text here does not aim to explain the HL7 FHIR standard as such nor does this guide aim to explain all the possibilities of the HL7 FHIR standard. For any exhaustive overview of the FHIR standard, the pages by HL7 are considered sufficient.</p>
<p>Instead, the focus of this guide is to give as pragmatic and concise as possible some extra pointers needed to create a valid HL7 FHIR laboratory result concerning a human patient in the Belgian context. The reader of this text shall take note of the FHIR artefacts that are also included in this Implementation Guide. The pointers given on this page cannot be fully understood without them.</p>
<p>Parts of constructing the laboratory report that are considered self-evident when examining the FHIR resources are not repeated here.</p>



<h3>Conventions</h3>
<a name="Note on values and decimal mark"> </a>
<h4>Note on values and decimal mark</h4>
<p>Values are always expressed with the 'full stop' or point (.) as decimal mark. Commas SHALL NOT be used to make numbers easier to read. (e.g. ten thousand is always written as '10000' – never as '10,000' or '10.000')</p>

<a name="UTF 8"> </a>
<h4>UTF 8</h4>
<p>The HL7 FHIR message is considered to be UTF-8. It is RECOMMENDED to declare the use of UTF-8 at the top when sending FHIR as XML.</p>

<a name="Use of codes"> </a>
<h4>Use of codes</h4>
<p>The different bindings with codes SHALL be examined when implementing the laboratory report. Specifically the use of codes to express the observations as expressed on this page infra SHALL be strictly followed. As a general back-up rule, whenever the laboratory does use a propriety code (e.g. to express a bodysite), a .text element SHALL always be included explaining the code.</p>
<a name="mustSupport"> </a>
<h4>mustSupport</h4>
<p>The marking of an element as 'mustSupport' might be a new concept when one is new to HL7 FHIR.</p>
<p>As expressed in the HL7 specifications, this marking actually
 is a functional concept more
 then it is used in a purely technical validation: "[…] mustSupport means that implementations that produce or consume 
 resources SHALL provide "support" for the element in some meaningful way."</p>  
<p>That is indeed the way this marking SHALL be understood in the profiles in this guide: elements
 marked mustSupport might provide meaningful information when produced or consumed
 and these parties SHALL deal with it in a meaningful way. 
 Note a mustSupport marking does not mean the element is mandatory – when that is the case, it is of course expressed in the cardinality.
</p>
<a name="The laboratory order"> </a>
<h3>The laboratory order</h3>
<p>A FHIR artefact to start the workflow with the order has also been created. As this builds on a base structure that is also proposed
for other referral prescriptions in Belgium, it is currently published within a different Implementation Guide.</p>
<p>The ordering profile starts from the base FHIR resource 'serviceRequests'. More details:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://build.fhir.org/ig/hl7-be/hl7-be-fhir-referral-prescription/guidance.html#guidance">General guidance</a>
 concerning the orders in Belgium and <a href="http://build.fhir.org/ig/hl7-be/hl7-be-fhir-referral-prescription/guidance.html#specifics-concerning-the-referral-prescription-for-laboratory">specific laboratory order guidance.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://build.fhir.org/ig/hl7-be/hl7-be-fhir-referral-prescription/StructureDefinition-be-lab-prescription.html">Technical definition</a> of the order for laboratory.</li>
<li>An <a href="http://build.fhir.org/ig/hl7-be/hl7-be-fhir-referral-prescription/ServiceRequest-laboratory-order-example1.html">example</a> for the order.</li>
</ul>


<a name="The structure of the report:attention points"> </a>
<h3>The structure of the report: attention points</h3>
<p>The content of the report is described in detail in the profiles. This chapter highlights some general attention points in the structure. </p>
<p>The profile defines cardinalities, preferred codesystems etc. As usual in the FHIR standard, it is equally important to take note of the different descriptions explaining the elements in the profile. These descriptions contain information that would otherwise by typically found in a cookbook explaining a technical structure element by element.</p>

<a name="Main FHIR resources of the report: the DiagnosticReport"> </a>
<h4>Main FHIR resources of the report: the DiagnosticReport</h4>
<p>The main FHIR resource to express the laboratory report is the DiagnosticReport. A Belgian profile has thus been created to use this resource in the intended fashion.</p>
<p>This DiagnosticReport is the 'organizer' of the report. It forms the high level structure around all the actual concrete information in the laboratory report e.g. the actual observations, the specimen, the patient etc.</p>
<a name="The Observation and the Specimen"> </a>
<h5>The Observation and the Specimen</h5>
<p>The most important content within the DiagnosticReport is expressed using the FHIR resources
 Observation and Specimen. Both have a specific Belgian profile to use in the DiagnosticReport.</p>
 <p>Unless the specimen is explicitly clear from the used LOINC code it SHALL be available in the report. 
 This means the specimen type itself but also the other functionalities of the Specimen resource 
 SHALL be leveraged <b>when needed</b> such as extra information about 
 where the specimen was taken (e.g. taken from left or right elbow).</p>
<a name="Referencing other FHIR resources"></a>
<h4>Referencing other FHIR resources</h4>
<p>As FHIR provides different resources, the DiagnosticReport will reference many other FHIR resources such as Patient, Practitioner, Specimen etc.</p>
<p>FHIR allows for <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/references.html">multiple ways to reference</a> other resources. For example, these other resources can be referenced using a URL to a server or they can be added in a bundle together with the DiagnosticReport to have everything available in one JSON or XML.</p>
<a name="General remarks on all the items"></a>
<h4>General remarks on all the items</h4>
<p>On the high level of the diagnosticReport, there is the possibility to a .conclusion (primitive string FHIR datatype) and/or a .conclusionCode element (CodeableConcept FHIR datatype, when needed to express using a code)</p>
<p>In both the important Resources Observation and Specimen there is the possibility to use the .note element (also a free text format, following the Annotation FHIR datatype.)</p>
<a name="Role of the narrative in FHIR"></a>
<h4>Role of the narrative in FHIR</h4>
<p>Implementers SHALL explicitely take note of the rules 
around the narrative in FHIR <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/narrative.html">as 
explained on the pages of HL7.</a></p>
<p>Specifically, the strong recommendation 
of HL7 concerning the use of the 
narrative "to support human-consumption as a fallback" 
is important in the context of the laboratory report.</p>
<p>A <b>structured Belgian laboratory report</b> means all content SHALL BE available in the structured elements. As such, a 
narrative with <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/valueset-narrative-status.html">
narrative-status 'additional'</a> SHALL NOT be used. 
Specifically, on the level of the individual Observation resources, 
that 'additional' status SHALL BE avoided.</p>
<p>In other words, in cases where a laboratory report cannot be expressed as a structured report, the narrative SHALL NOT be
used as a fallback. 
In that case, it is preferred the element to present the report as PDF SHALL be used and the resulting report
in that case is <b>NOT</b> considered to be a structured Belgian laboratory report.</p>
<a name="Specimen overview"></a>
<h4>Specimen overview</h4>
<p>Every specimen is expressed as a seperate Specimen resource in FHIR.</p>
<p>In the DiagnosticReport.specimen element, all the specimen are referenced.</p>
<p>The actual Observations refer to these Specimen.</p>
<a name="Grouping of observations using Observation resources"></a>
<h4>Grouping of observations using Observation resources</h4>
<p>Naturally, the Observation resource is heavily used in the laboratory report.</p>
<p>It SHALL be noted, the FHIR DiagnosticReport base standard resource takes a <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/diagnosticreport.html#bnc">pragmatic approach</a> to dealing with the multiple observations.</p>
<p>Basically, to fully understand the DiagnosticReport and the Observation resource it is key to understand a <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/observation.html#obsgrouping">few basic distinct ways to group observations</a> and how they cater to different use cases:</p>
<ol>
<li>Using the .result of the DiagnosticReport resource to reference 0..* Observation: that way multiple Observations are referenced in the root of the report. These will cater to reports that give back 0..* results without any complex structure between the results. These Observation resource might however leverage more complex structures by also following the strategy described in the following options.</li>
<li>The Observation itself may include 0..* .component elements. A component element within an Observation is a list of key/value pairs with optionally for each key/value pair a data absent reason and/or an interpretation code and/or a referenceRange. Such a list of key/value pairs is considered to be part of one Observation. A typical example is to include systolic and diastolic component observations for blood pressure measurement. "Components should only be used when there is only one method, one observation, one performer, one device, and one time."</li>
<li>The Observation may be part of a group of Observation resources. This is established by using the .hasMember in the Observation. Typically, this is used for a panel or battery where the panel code is given without a value in the parent Observation and the actual results are seperate Observation resources referenced from that parent Observation.</li>
</ol>
<p>To summarize, including 0..* Observation in a report always happens by using the first method. These Observation resources might be (relatively) simple or have a complex structure leveraging the two other methods.</p>
<a name="Using subtitles"></a>
<h4>Using subtitles</h4>
<p>An important requirement is the ability to use subtitles in the structure of the laboratory report.</p>
<p>This can be done in the report by leveraging the third way to use observations grouping supra. When doing this with the goal of only adding a subtitle, the CodeableConcept datatype of the .code element in the parent Observation will minimally contain the .text element.</p>
<a name="Important time elements"></a>
<h3>Important time elements</h3>

<p>This chapter gives a quick overview of where to find the most important time elements in a laboratory report.</p>
<a name="Time of the prescription"></a>
<h4>Time of the prescription</h4>
<p>The time of the prescription lives in the original ServiceRequest resource that is referenced in the DiagnosticReport.basedOn element. The time of the prescription lives in the ServiceRequest.authoredOn element.</p>
<a name="Time of the specimen collection"></a>
<h4>Time of the specimen collection</h4>
<p>This can be expressed in the DiagnosticReport.effectiveDateTime or DiagnosticReport.effectivePeriod element. This is overruled when this is also expressed as part of the Specimen resource that is referenced from within the diagnostic report. The Specimen.collection.collected element gives the dateTime or period of the collection.</p>
<a name="Time of the specimen reception"></a>
<h4>Time of the specimen reception</h4>
<p>This is part of the Specimen resource that is referenced from within the diagnostic report. The Specimen.receivedTime element
 gives the dateTime of reception.</p>
 <a name="Time when the report is made available"></a>
<h4>Time when the report is made available</h4>
<p>This is the DiagnosticReport.issued element.</p>
<a name="Effective vs Issued"></a>
<h3>Effective vs Issued</h3>
<p>It shall be noted the DiagnosticReport, Specimen and Observation resources all have .effective and .issued elements. There is an important difference between these.</p>
<p>The .effective element mostly points to the time of the specific procedure or specimen collection. The .issued element really is about when this was made available to providers, typically after review and/or verification. Please refer to the detailed descriptions in the FHIR standard for further information.</p>
<a name="Versioning of reports"></a>
<h3>Versioning of reports</h3>
<p>The base FHIR resource DiagnosticReport is of the FHIR type DomainResource and as such it inherits the base FHIR resource elements. In its root, it inherits the elements defined in the base Resource FHIR datatype. This includes the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/R4/resource.html#Meta">Resource Metadata</a>.</p>
<p>The Resource Metadata contains in its .versionId the actual version of the DiagnosticReport.</p>
<p>The laboratory report SHALL also identify itself using a business identifier in the DiagnosticReport.
The combination of system and identifier needs to be globally unique. Typically, the laboratory assigns an identifier that will remain the same during eventual different versions.</p>
<p>Some extra data concerning the status of the DiagnosticReport report can be found in its .status element. This element provides the <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/valueset-diagnostic-report-status.html">possibility to add a status like 'corrected', 'final' etc.</a> It is noted also the Observation resources that are part of the report have in their structure each also a .status element. Naturally, the different statuses should be logical.</p>
<a name="Relating reports (replacing, updating)"></a>
<h3>Relating reports (replacing, updating)</h3>
<p>As described supra, the report has a status. As such, a new version of the report might be a correction. A new version is however still
the same report.</p>
<p>For example, as the vital element of a laboratory report, the Observation, also carries a distinct status (https://www.hl7.org/fhir/valueset-observation-status.html ) 
It is up to a receiving consumer, when it receives a new version of a report to correctly interpret any change in statuses on an Observation. 
When a diagnosticReport is solicited by a party, it should 
always receive the most up to date version and again, it is up to the consuming party to correctly interpret statuses.</p>



<a name="Referencing the (sub)order"></a>
<h3>Referencing the (sub)order</h3>
<p>The order (ServiceRequest resource) that is referenced from the DiagnosticReport via its .basedOn element contains the time when this order was placed as well as the original order number.</p>
<p>It is possible for one or more of the Observations to reference a different ServiceRequest by using the .basedOn element in the Observation. This can be used e.g. if needed to explicitely state an Observation was made via a sub order. It is noted the Observation also contains the element .performer to simply specify the Observation had a different performer from the main performer referenced from the DiagnosticReport resource.</p>  
<a name="Adding a PDF representation"></a>
<h3>Adding a PDF representation</h3>
<p>If needed to also include the report as a PDF, that is possible using the element .presentedForm. Please refer to the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/R4/datatypes.html#Attachment">FHIR complex datatype 'Attachment'</a> for further instructions how to do include this.</p> <p>Naturally, the sender of the report that adds a PDF representation SHALL ensure it remains clinically logical and safe with the way the data is otherwise structurally expressed in the resource.</p>
<a name="Guidance for codes and values in the Observation resource"></a>
<h3>Guidance for codes and values in the Observation resource</h3>
<a name="Use of Retam codes"></a>
<h4>Use of Retam codes</h4>
<p>The implementer SHALL adhere to the preferred codes to use in the .code element as described here</p>
<p>The recommended codification used is LOINC as per the subset defined by the FPS Health, for the majority of commonly used lab measurements and demands. This subset is available on the <a href="https://www.vas.ehealth.fgov.be/webretam/retam/home.htm">website of the FPS Health</a>.</p>

<p>
It is allowed to use multiple codes within the FHIR CodeableConcept datatype. But the code given must follow the following rules.</p>
<ol>
<li> The actual observation is preferably coded in LOINC (subset as defined by FPS Health)<ul><li><pre>"code":{
	"coding":[
		{
			"system": "http://loinc.org",
			"code": "30341-2",
			"display": "Erythrocyte sedimentation rate"
		}
		]
	}</pre></li></ul></li>
<li> If above not possible , ALBERT codes are used (subset as defined by FPS Health) 
<ul><li><pre>"code":{
	"coding":[
		{
			"system": "https://www.ehealth.fgov.be/standards/fhir/CodeSystem/albert",
			"code": "26224",
			"display": "Glucose (urine 24h)"
		}
		]
	}</pre></li></ul></li>
<li> If above not possible,laboratory sends its own code plus obligatory a text element to further explain.<ul><li><pre>"code":{
	"coding":[
		{
			"system": "OWNSYSTEM",
			"code": "OWNCODE",
			"display": "DISPLAYOWNCODE"
		}
		],
	"text": "TEXTEXPLAINING"
	}</pre></li></ul></li>
<li> If above not possible the kind of observation is expressed only in text (allowed but not recommended)<ul><li><pre>"code":{
	"text": "TEXTEXPLAINING"
	}</pre></li></ul></li>
	</ol>
	<p> If needed, it is always possible to add extra translations in the display using the HL7 translation extension as such<pre>"code":{
          "coding": [
            {
              "system": "http://loinc.org",
              "code": "18723-7",
              "display": "Hematology studies (set)",
              "_display": {
                "extension": [
                  {
                    "url": "http://hl7.org/fhir/StructureDefinition/translation",
                    "extension": [
                      {
                        "url": "lang",
                        "valueCode": "be-nl"
                      },
                      {
                        "url": "content",
                        "valueString": "HEMATOLOGIE"
                      }
                    ]
                  }
                ]
              }
            }
          ]
        }</pre></p>
	
<a name="Expression of results"></a>
<h4>Expression of results</h4>
<ul><li>
Typically, values will be expressed using a certain unit.
Units will be expressed using <a href="http://unitsofmeasure.org/ucum.html">UCUM codes</a> as per the specification. The KMEHR reference table CD-UNIT is not used.
It remains technically possible to express units using a different way. However, as UCUM provides a standardized syntax to 
express in theory any type of exotic unit, it is HIGHLY RECOMMENDED to always use the UCUM way to express units.</li>
<li>Implementers SHALL take note of the very flexible .value[x] element within the FHIR Observation resource. This allows multiple ways to express the result structurally. Each option has its own datatype. Typically, for measurements, .valueQuantity is expected to be used that leverages the FHIR Quantity datatype. For observation results that do not fall in any structured category, there is the option to use .valueString to express the result in text.
</li></ul>
<a name="Use of preformatted text"></a>
<h4>Use of preformatted text</h4>
<p>If the Observation can only be fully expressed in preformatted text, this is NOT RECOMMENDED but possible by only providing the mininal required elements in the Observation resource and using the 'pre' tag to include this in the narrative. As such, the Observation will not contain a structured .value and the narrative will normally be marked as ''additional.'</p>
<a name="Relative time for challenge testing"></a>
<h4>Relative time for challenge testing</h4>
<p>Some LOINC codes exist that define a specific timing interval as ‘XXX’. E.g.“LOINC 16904-5 GLUCOSE^1ST SPECIMEN POST XXX CHALLENGE” but without a timing interval.
If the Code needs to be 'qualified' with a relative time: use the .component structure to do this.</p>
<p><pre>
{
  "resourceType" : "Observation",
[...]
  "code" : {
    "coding" : [
      {
        "system" : "http://loinc.org",
        "code" : "53093-1",
        "display" : "Glucose^post XXX challenge"
      }
    ]
  },
[...]
  "valueQuantity" : {
    "value" : 9.1,
    "unit" : "mmol/l",
    "system" : "http://unitsofmeasure.org",
    "code" : "mmol/l"
  },
  "component" : [
    {
      "code" : {
        "coding" : [
          {
            "system" : "http://snomed.info/sct",
            "code" : "118578006",
            "display" : "Relative time"
          }
        ]
      },
      "valueQuantity" : {
        "value" : 180,
        "unit" : "m",
        "system" : "http://unitsofmeasure.org",
        "code" : "m"
      }
    }
  ]
}
[...]
</pre></p>

<a name="Use of images"></a>
<h3>Use of images</h3>
<p>Note, when it is needed to include a PDF representation, there exists a seperate element for that cfr. supra</p>
<p>If there is a need to add images in general to the report, 
they can be referenced from the diagnosticReport resource itself via the .media element.
A typical example would be to include a scatter diagram.</p>
<p>Such images SHALL be available in the exchanged message itself. (Meaning the Media resource
contains the full Base64 and this resource is available as seperate resource in a FHIR Bundle or as a contained
resource in the DiagnosticReport.) </p> 
<a name="Caution concerning the size of images"></a>
<h4>Caution concerning the size of images</h4>
<p>Use of images SHALL be done with caution towards consumers concerning possible heavy payloads.</p>
<p>
Many elements are available within the Media resource to further define, 
in the below example, minimal use is made of the Media resource to only highlight the bare essentials. 
This limited use of this resource in this
guide was a very conscious choice as it appears the Media resource
 is abanded in future FHIR versions in favor of the DocumentReference resource.
The impact of that will however be minimal as both use the FHIR datatype Attachment to express the actual content.
<pre>
"resource" : {
        "resourceType" : "Media",
     [...] 
        "status" : "completed",
        "content" : {
		[This element is of the FHIR datatype Attachment]
          "contentType": "image/gif",
          "data": "R0lGODlhfgCRAPcAAAAAAIAAAACAAI[...]"
        }
      }
</pre></p>

<a name="Guidance for antibiogram structures"></a>
<h3>Guidance for antibiogram structures</h3>
<p>The HL7 pages describe how to deal with more complex antibiogram structures. In <a href="https://www.hl7.org/fhir/R4/diagnosticreport-examples.html#10.3.7.1.1">these rules</a>, examples
 are given how to deal with multiple levels to model the organisms and susceptibility panels.</p>
 <p>The 'AntibiogramAsBundleCollection' example that can be found in this guide is based on the second structure described on that page</p>
 <p>It basically leverages the third way as described supra how to group resources:</p>
 <ul>
  <li>Any general Observation that is done is on the level of the report.</li>
 <li>For each organism there is an Observation on the level of the report: the 'organism observation'
 <ul>
 <li>Every panel Observation on the organism is referenced via a .hasMember in that 'organism observation'</li>  
 </ul>
 
 </li>
</ul>
<a name="Codification of organisms"></a>
<h4>Codification of organisms</h4>
<p>Organisms are preferably expressed in SNOMED-CT as such:</p>
<pre> "coding" : [
            {
              "system" : "http://snomed.info/sct",
              "code" : "243301005",
              "display" : "Morganella morganii"
            }
          ]</pre>

<a name="Guidance for minimal information in supporting resources"></a>
<h3>Guidance for minimal information in supporting resources</h3>
<a name="Minimal information concerning the subjec"></a>
<h4>Minimal information concerning the subject</h4>
<p>An .identifier (SSIN if possible) SHALL be given.</p>
<p>If the identifier is the only information to send concerning the patient, it is allowed to use a FHIR logical reference to refer to the patient. 
Thus avoiding the need to include a full Patient resource or a reference to a full Patient resource on a server. A logical reference will lead to such a structure:</p>
 <pre>
  &lt;subject&gt;
     &lt;identifier>
        &lt;system value="https://www.ehealth.fgov.be/standards/fhir/NamingSystem/ssin"/&gt;
	&lt;value value="79121137740"/&gt;
     &lt;/identifier&gt;
   &lt;/subject&gt;
  </pre>
<p>Some additional minimal information concerning the subject (Patient resource), besides the identifier, SHOULD however be given if available:a .name, at least one .telecom, a .birthDate and a .address. In any Patient resource, the .gender SHALL be given (but could be 'unknown'.)</p>
<a name="Minimal information concerning the laboratory"></a>
<h4>Minimal information concerning the laboratory</h4>
<p>Some minimal information concerning the laboratory (Organization resource) SHOULD be given: an .identifier (NIHDI if possible), a .name, at least one .telecom and a .address.</p>
<a name="Minimal information concerning the laboratory responsible"></a>
<h4>Minimal information concerning the laboratory responsible</h4>
<p>Some minimal information concerning the laboratory responsible (Practitioner resource) SHOULD be given: an .identifier (NIHDI if possible), a .name, at least one .telecom and a .address</p>
<a name="Minimal information concerning other healthcare parties"></a>
<h4>Minimal information concerning other healthcare parties</h4>
<p>Some minimal information concerning other healthcare parties (Practitioner resource), if they are used, SHOULD be given: an .identifier (NIHDI if possible), a .name, at least one .telecom and a .address</p>

<a name="FHIR technical implementation specifics"></a>
  <h3>FHIR technical implementation specifics</h3>
  <a name="The federal IG"></a>
  <h4>The federal IG</h4>
<p>This guide uses the artefacts and guidance as they are defined in <a href="https://www.ehealth.fgov.be/standards/kmehr/en/page/fhir-profiles">the official federal IG as published by eHealth Platform</a>. Implementers SHALL take note of the guidelines defined in that IG. Please take note when you are technically validating against the IG described on this page you also need that IG for the base federal profiles.</p>
<a name="Technical implementation of the specification published here"></a>
<h4>Technical implementation of the specification published here</h4>
<p>As per the FHIR standard specifications, there are multiple ways in how the report can be exchanged or requested.</p>
<p>A POC phase for this project during 2021 is investigating possibilities.</p>
<p>Current expectations (at publication date of this draft IG) for the first iteration of the laboratory flows are:</p>
<ul>
<li>The laboratory prescription will be send as a serviceRequest complying with the Belgian laboratory prescription profile with all needed artefacts as 'contained'</li>
<li>The laboratory result will be send as a diagnosticReport complying with the Belgian laboratory result profile with all needed artefacts either as 'contained' or as seperate entries in a FHIR 'bundle' </li>
</ul>


</div>