

<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd" >


<p>This Visualisation Guidance page aims to give guidance about which of the structured elements available in a diagnosticreport SHALL be minimally visualised and in what kind of structure
they SHALL be minimally presented to safely understand them.</p>
<p>This is not a guidance page on the actual report, the thumb of rule here concerning the referenced elements is: this is where they 
SHALL be visualized IF they are available in the report. Please refer to the other pages in this guide for guidance
on how to construct the report. It is up to a human inspection to finally judge the quality of the
report that is visualized following the rules on this page.</p>
<p>This page does NOT aim to give exhaustive guidance how the final user friendly visualization should be like - that is 
considered the domain of any consuming system.</p>
<p>Whenever a specific element is given infra (e.g. '.identifier') without extra explication, 
it is implied any subelements of this element that are available SHALL be displayed. Also, if the element repeats, the repeats SHALL be visualized. </p>


<a name="General information"> </a>
<h3>General information</h3>
<p>Status</p>
<ul>
<li>.status</li>
</ul>
<p>Identifier(s) of the reports</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>One general title</p>
<ul>
<li>.code</li>
</ul>
<p>Extra category(ies) applicable to this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.category</li>
</ul>
<p>Effective</p>
<ul>
<li>.effective[x]</li>
</ul>
<p>Issue date of this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.issued</li>
</ul>
<p>General conclusions based on this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.conclusion</li>
<li>.conclusionCode</li>
</ul>

<a name="Patient"> </a>
<h3>Patient(.subject)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected a patient may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
<p>Birthdate</p>
<ul>
<li>.birthDate</li>
</ul>
<p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
<p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>

<a name="Performer"> </a>
<h3>Performer(.performer)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected the performer(s) (here it is assumed they are of the Practitioner and/or Organization type) may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
<p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
<p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>

<a name="Specimen"> </a>
<h3>Specimen(.specimen)</h3>
<p>To do</p>

<a name="Observation"> </a>
<h3>Observation(.observation)</h3>
<p>To do</p>

<a name=".."> </a>
<h3>..</h3>
<p>To do</p>

</div>