

<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd" >


<p>This Visualisation Guidance page aims to give guidance about
 which of the structured elements available in a diagnosticreport SHALL be <b>minimally</b> visualised
  and in what kind of structure
they SHALL be minimally presented to safely understand them.</p>
<p>This is not a guidance page on the actual report, the thumb of rule here concerning the referenced elements is: this is to be
visualized IF they are available in the report. Please refer to the other pages in this guide for guidance
on how to construct the report. It is up to a human inspection to finally judge the quality of the
report that is visualized following the rules on this page.</p>



<table style="width:70%;border: 1px solid black;border-collapse: collapse;" >
 <tr>
  <td><b>PLEASE NOTE: This page does NOT aim to give exhaustive guidance how any user friendly presentation should be like when the structured elements are structurally integrated in a patient dossier - that is 
considered the domain of any consuming system.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><b>PLEASE NOTE: Whenever a specific element is given infra (e.g. '.identifier') without extra explication, 
it is implied any sub elements of this element that are available SHALL be displayed. Also, if the element repeats, the repeats SHALL be visualized. </b></td>
</tr>
</table>



<p>Considerations concerning a creation of a federal visualisation tool:
<ul>
<li>It is highly RECOMMENDED that any initiative towards a general visualisation
 investigates possibilities by using the FHIR narrative. This can take the form
  of tuned narrative templates <a href="https://hapifhir.io/hapi-fhir/docs/model/narrative_generation.html">as is described e.g. in the Java FHIR Hapi libraries.</a>
</li>
<li>
Any mechanisms that automate visualisation SHALL also run a technical validation against the used FHIR profiles
before returning any visualisation. An automated mechanism SHALL NOT return any visualised form of a laboratory report when a technical validation contains errors.
</li>
<li>
Visualisation SHALL be in such a way the information is presented in a tabular fashion.
</li>
<li>
Considering the above, it is highly RECOMMENDED a generic visualisation module for the FHIR laboratory report takes the form of an endpoint where
developers or testers can post a FHIR document bundle and receive in their answer the FHIR document with generated narrative.
</li>
</ul>
</p>


<a name="General information"> </a>
<h3>General information (DiagnosticReport)</h3>
<p>Status</p>
<ul>
<li>.status</li>
</ul>
<p>Identifier(s) of the reports</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>One general title</p>
<ul>
<li>.code</li>
</ul>
<p>Extra category(ies) applicable to this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.category</li>
</ul>
<p>Effective(Time of the specimen collection
 - is overruled when collection time is given in .specimen element.)</p>
<ul>
<li>.effective[x]</li>
</ul>
<p>Issue date of this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.issued</li>
</ul>
<p>General conclusions based on this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.conclusion</li>
<li>.conclusionCode</li>
</ul>
<a name="Time of prescription"> </a>
<h3>Time of prescription(DiagnosticReport.basedOn)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected the original prescription may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Authored on</p>
<ul>
<li>.authoredOn</li>
</ul>

<a name="Patient"> </a>
<h3>Patient(DiagnosticReport.subject)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected a patient may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
<p>Birthdate</p>
<ul>
<li>.birthDate</li>
</ul>
<p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
<p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>

<a name="Performer"> </a>
<h3>Performer(DiagnosticReport.performer)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected the performer(s) (here it is assumed they are of the Practitioner and/or Organization type) may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
<p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
<p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>

<a name="Results interpreter"> </a>
<h3>Results interpreter(DiagnosticReport.resultsInterpreter)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected the results interpreter(s) (here it is assumed they are of the Practitioner and/or Organization type) may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised. If this is the same entity as the performer supra, this MAY be omitted for readability purposes.</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
<p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
<p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>





<a name="Specimen"> </a>
<h3>Specimen(DiagnosticReport.specimen)</h3>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Status</p>
<ul>
<li>.status</li>
</ul>
<p>Type</p>
<ul>
<li>.type</li>
</ul>
<p>Received time</p>
<ul>
<li>.receivedTime</li>
</ul>
<p>Parent specimen (It is possible a specimen refers to a parent specimen(s), from which it originated. In that case
 the specimen SHALL clearly state this
by giving the identifier(s). The actual parent specimen(s) SHALL be visualized as seperate specimen.)</p>
<ul>
<li>.parent.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Collection details (All subelements available under the .collection element SHALL be visualized when available (e.g. when they were collected, the method
of collection etc.)</p>
<ul>
<li>.collection</li>
</ul>
<p>Processing details (All subelements available under the .processing element SHALL be visualized when available (e.g. a specific procedure that was done)</p>
<ul>
<li>.processing</li>
</ul>
<p>Condition</p>
<ul>
<li>.condition</li>
</ul>
<p>Notes (Any free text note to explain something concerning the specimen)</p>
<ul>
<li>.note</li>
</ul>

<a name="Observation"> </a>
<h3>Observation(DiagnosticReport.observation)</h3>
<p>As a general guidance concerning the visualisation of the observations any visualisation mechanism SHALL take note an observation
MAY have components (.component element) and an observation MAY have member observations (.hasMember element). If any of these structures exists, a visualisation mechanism
SHALL present these structures in a hierarchical fashion. Cfr. infra for specific guidance in specific reports</p>
<p><b>When visualizing a CodeableConcept:
<ul>
<li>Visualisation mechanisms SHALL display the value given in CodeableConcept.text</li>
<li>If that is not available, it SHALL display a value given in CodeableConcept.coding.display (if there are multiple .coding and one has the .userSelected flag: it SHALL take that)</li>
</ul>
</b></p>
<p>Status (For readability purposes a status of 'final' MAY be hidden)</p>
<ul>
<li>.status</li>
</ul>
<p>Category (NB remark supra 'When visualizing a CodeableConcept')</p>
<ul>
<li>.category</li>
</ul>
<p>Code (NB this is the main code to identify the Observation. When an Observation is used as a title, it may happen no
actual code is available in the .code element but this title will be available in the .code.text element.) (NB remark supra 'When visualizing a CodeableConcept')</p>
<ul>
<li>.code</li>
</ul>
<p>Effective time (the clinically relevant time of of the observation)</p>
<ul>
<li>.effective[x]</li>
</ul>
<p>Issued time (time this observation was made available)</p>
<ul>
<li>.time </li>
</ul>
<p>Performer (observation.performer)</p>
<p>It is fully expected the performer(s) (here it is assumed they are of the Practitioner and/or Organization type) may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>For readability purposes, it is RECOMMENDED to only visualise the performer here when it is available and different from the performer
in the root of the diagnosticreport</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Value (Special attention SHALL be given to also correctly visualize any unit)</p>
<ul>
<li>.value[x]</li>
</ul>
<p>Data absent (NB remark supra 'When visualizing a CodeableConcept')</p>
<ul>
<li>.dataAbsentReason</li>
</ul>
<p>Interpretation (NB remark supra 'When visualizing a CodeableConcept')</p>
<ul>
<li>.interpretation</li>
</ul>
<p>Reference Range</p>
<ul>
<li>.referenceRange</li>
</ul>
<p>Bodysite (NB remark supra 'When visualizing a CodeableConcept')</p>
<ul>
<li>.bodySite</li>
</ul>
<p>Method  (NB remark supra 'When visualizing a CodeableConcept'</p>
<ul>
<li>.method</li>
</ul>
<p>Specimen  (observation.specimen)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>

<p>Notes</p>
<p>The .note element MAY contain an author and a time. The author MAY be omitted for readability purposes if it is the same as
the performer of the Observation (when the performer is omitted already because it is the same as the performer in the DiagnosticReport it follows the author of the note, in case
it is again the same is also omitted)</p>
<ul>
<li>.note</li>
</ul>




<a name="Extra visualisation guidance concerning antibiogram"> </a>
<h4>Extra visualisation guidance concerning antibiogram</h4>
<p>A typical structure in an antibiogram is a 'master' observation that has a member Observation for each culture.
Each of these members will have a member list for all the susceptibilities of that culture.</p>
<p>The rules around hierarchical fashion as described supra apply here but the visualisation for an antibiogram SHALL
be to visualise these susceptibility lists in columns. (Giving the name of the antibiotic only once and expressing the different 
susceptibilities for the different cultures as columns that are cleary marked to which culture they apply) This means for readibility purposes, only the .interpration element is considered from the susceptibility Observation.</p>
<p>Example:</p>
<pre>[...]
Culture	1.Morganella morganii    
	2.Escherichia coli
	
Antibiogram							1			2
			Ampicilin				R			S
			Trimethoprim+Sulfamethoxazole		S			S
			Nitrofurantoin				R			S
			Cefuroxime				R			S
			Gentamicin				S			S
			Colistin				R			S
[...]</pre>


<a name="Extra visualisation guidance concerning reports only available as pdf"> </a>
<h4>Extra visualisation guidance concerning reports only available as pdf</h4>
<p>A report that does not contain any structured information concerning the observations is not considered to be a structured
Belgian laboratory report but technically, the format still allows for this. A proper visualisation for the results in those kind of reports is the
rendering of the pdf that will live in the .presentedForm element.</p>

</div>