

<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd" >


<p>This Visualisation Guidance page aims to give guidance about which of the structured elements available in a diagnosticreport SHALL be minimally visualised and in what kind of structure
they SHALL be minimally presented to safely understand them.</p>
<p>This is not a guidance page on the actual report, the thumb of rule here concerning the referenced elements is: this is where they 
SHALL be visualized IF they are available in the report. Please refer to the other pages in this guide for guidance
on how to construct the report. It is up to a human inspection to finally judge the quality of the
report that is visualized following the rules on this page.</p>
<p>This page does NOT aim to give exhaustive guidance how the final user friendly visualization should be like - that is 
considered the domain of any consuming system.</p>
<p>Whenever a specific element is given infra (e.g. '.identifier') without extra explication, 
it is implied any subelements of this element that are available SHALL be displayed. Also, if the element repeats, the repeats SHALL be visualized. </p>


<a name="General information"> </a>
<h3>General information</h3>
<p>Status</p>
<ul>
<li>.status</li>
</ul>
<p>Identifier(s) of the reports</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>One general title</p>
<ul>
<li>.code</li>
</ul>
<p>Extra category(ies) applicable to this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.category</li>
</ul>
<p>Effective</p>
<ul>
<li>.effective[x]</li>
</ul>
<p>Issue date of this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.issued</li>
</ul>
<p>General conclusions based on this report</p>
<ul>
<li>.conclusion</li>
<li>.conclusionCode</li>
</ul>
<a name="Time of prescription"> </a>
<h3>Time of prescription(.basedOn)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected the original prescription may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Authored on</p>
<ul>
<li>.authoredOn</li>
</ul>

<a name="Patient"> </a>
<h3>Patient(.subject)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected a patient may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
<p>Birthdate</p>
<ul>
<li>.birthDate</li>
</ul>
<p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
<p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>

<a name="Performer"> </a>
<h3>Performer(.performer)</h3>
<p>It is fully expected the performer(s) (here it is assumed they are of the Practitioner and/or Organization type) may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
<p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
<p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>

<a name="Specimen"> </a>
<h3>Specimen(.specimen)</h3>
<p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Status</p>
<ul>
<li>.status</li>
</ul>
<p>Type</p>
<ul>
<li>.type</li>
</ul>
<p>Received time</p>
<ul>
<li>.receivedTime</li>
</ul>
<p>Parent specimen (It is possible a specimen refers to a parent specimen(s), from which it originated. In that case
 the specimen SHALL clearly state this
by giving the identifier(s). The actual parent specimen(s) SHALL be visualized as seperate specimen.)</p>
<ul>
<li>.parent.identifier</li>
</ul>
<p>Collection details (All subelements available under the .collection element SHALL be visualized when available (e.g. when they were collected, the method
of collection etc.)</p>
<ul>
<li>.collection</li>
</ul>
<p>Processing details (All subelements available under the .processing element SHALL be visualized when available (e.g. a specific procedure that was done)</p>
<ul>
<li>.processing</li>
</ul>
<p>Condition</p>
<ul>
<li>.condition</li>
</ul>
<p>Notes (Any free text note to explain something concerning the specimen)</p>
<ul>
<li>.note</li>
</ul>

<a name="Observation"> </a>
<h3>Observation(.observation)</h3>
<p>As a general guidance concerning the visualisation of the observations any visualisation mechanism SHALL take note an observation
MAY have components and an observation MAY have member observations. If any of these structures exists, a visualisation mechanism
SHALL present these structures in a hierarchical fashion.</p>

<p>Status (For readability purposes a status of 'final' MAY be hidden)</p>
<ul>
<li>.status</li>
</ul>
<p>Category</p>
<ul>
<li>.category</li>
</ul>
<p>Code (NB this is the main code to identify the Observation. When an Observation is used as a title, it may happen no
actual code is available in the .code element but this title will be available in the .code.text element.)</p>
<ul>
<li>.code</li>
</ul>
<p>Effective time (the clinically relevant time of of the observation)</p>
<ul>
<li>.effective[x]</li>
</ul>
<p>Issued time</p>
<ul>
<li>.time this observation was made available</li>
</ul>
<p>It is fully expected the performer(s) (here it is assumed they are of the Practitioner and/or Organization type) may not be exhaustively available in the report. 
However, if available, the following elements SHALL be visualised</p>
<p>For readability purposes, it is RECOMMENDED to only visualise the performer here when it is available and different from the performer
in the root of the diagnosticreport</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Identifier(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.identifier</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Name(s)</p>
<ul>
<li>.name</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Telecom</p>
<ul>
<li>.telecom</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Address</p>
<ul>
<li>.address</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Value (Special attention SHALL be given to also correctly visualize any unit)</p>
<



<a name="Extra visualisation guidance concerning antibiogram"> </a>
<h4>Extra visualisation guidance concerning antibiogram</h4>
<p>A typical structure in an antibiogram is a 'master' observation that has a member Observation for each culture.
Each of these members will have a member list for all the susceptibilities.</p>
<p>Of course, the rules around hierarchical fashion as described supra apply here as well. The typical visualisation for an antibiogram would
be to visualise these susceptibility lists in columns. (Giving the name of the antibiotic once and expressing the different 
susceptibilities for the different cultures as columns that are cleary marked to which culture they apply)</p>
<p>Example:</p>
<pre>[...]
Culture	1.Morganella morganii    
	2.Escherichia coli
	
Antibiogram							1			2
			Ampicilin				R			S
			Trimethoprim+Sulfamethoxazole		S			S
			Nitrofurantoin				R			S
			Cefuroxime				R			S
			Gentamicin				S			S
			Colistin				R			S
[...]</pre>

</div>